export const MANAGEMENTINLIVINGA2018 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Some of the benefits of acquiring knowledge and skills in management in living are; it  \nI. equips individuals with coping skills in the rapid changing society  \nII. equips individuals with the financial resources for successful home keeping  \nIII. helps individuals influence the outcome of situations in orderly manner  \nIV. helps individuals manage available resources and control events of life",
A: "I, II and III only",
B: "II, III and IV only",
C: "I, II and IV only",
D: "I, III and IV only",
answer: "D. I, III and IV only",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Due to the varied nature of individual and family needs, management in living covers",
A: "all the issues of the family",
B: "specific area of study",
C: "the limited resources of the family",
D: "wide area of study",
answer: "D. wide area of study",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. One development characteristic of boys is",
A: "breaking of voice",
B: "broadening of hips",
C: "development of breast",
D: "menstruation",
answer: "A. breaking of voice",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The beginning of menstruation usually indicates a girl’s readiness for",
A: "child bearing",
B: "dating",
C: "marriage",
D: "sexual intercourse",
answer: "A. child bearing",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Adolescents emotional development are usually characterised by",
A: "excessive freedom",
B: "increased appetite",
C: "mood swings",
D: "wet dreams",
answer: "C. mood swings",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. An arrangement between people of the opposite sex co go out together mainly to socialise and have fun is",
A: "courtship",
B: "dating",
C: "engagement",
D: "marriage",
answer: "B. dating",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Factors that may lead to failure include  \nI. effective communication  \nII. infertility  \nIII. lack of commitment  \nIV. mistrust",
A: "I, II and III only",
B: "II, III and IV only",
C: "I, II and IV only",
D: "I, III and IV only",
answer: "B. II, III and IV only",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Early marriage usually leads to",
A: "acquisition of riches",
B: "barrenness",
C: "career achievement",
D: "teenage pregnancy",
answer: "D. teenage pregnancy",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The process of introducing semi-solid food to a baby’s diet is",
A: "artificial feeding",
B: "bottle feeding",
C: "nurturing",
D: "weaning",
answer: "D. weaning",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Child labour is",
A: "a source of training for the child",
B: "beneficial to the child economically",
C: "detrimental to the child’s development",
D: "Good for the country’s economy",
answer: "C. detrimental to the child’s development",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Likes, dislikes and desires which influence a person’s decisions are his/her",
A: "goals",
B: "needs",
C: "values",
D: "wanes",
answer: "C. values",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. When plans do not work out as anticipated",
A: "adjustment must be made",
B: "friends must be approached for help",
C: "they must be abandoned",
D: "they must be changed",
answer: "A. adjustment must be made",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. One of the decisions taken during the planning process in management is",
A: "changing standards",
B: "clarifying goals",
C: "revising goals",
D: "supervising activities",
answer: "B. clarifying goals",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. When parents separate or divorce, the children adjust better when they maintain good relationship with",
A: "both parents",
B: "parent’s relatives",
C: "their father",
D: "their mother",
answer: "A. both parents",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. To identify specific resources for effective planning, one requires",
A: "adjustment",
B: "information",
C: "motivation",
D: "organization",
answer: "B. information",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The resource which is needed most in doing strenuous work in the home is",
A: "capability",
B: "energy",
C: "skill",
D: "time",
answer: "B. energy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. A well designed house should",
A: "have big and spacious rooms for everybody",
B: "have all the bedrooms in one area of the house",
C: "have the plumbing well concealed from people",
D: "meet the needs and lifestyle of all the people",
answer: "D. meet the needs and lifestyle of all the people",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The practical application of measures to protect, preserve and improve health best describe",
A: "environmental hygiene",
B: "sanitation",
C: "personal hygiene",
D: "pollution",
answer: "A. environmental hygiene",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The appropriate procedure for scrubbing floors is to",
A: "scrub small area at a time and wipe",
B: "scrub the whole floor and wipe",
C: "pour soapy water on the floor and sweep",
D: "wet the floor to loosen diet and scrub",
answer: "A. scrub small area at a time and wipe",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Mildly scented flowers are most suitable for the",
A: "bedroom",
B: "dining table",
C: "centre table",
D: "kitchen",
answer: "A. bedroom",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Air pollution is caused by",
A: "chemicals from factories",
B: "fumes emitted by cars",
C: "human waste",
D: "waste from households",
answer: "B. fumes emitted by cars",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Saving time, avoiding too much thinking and walking, can be achieved in a home by creating",
A: "serving zone",
B: "social zone",
C: "work centres",
D: "work surfaces",
answer: "C. work centres",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Financial security of a family means that the family",
A: "is able to provide the present and future needs if members",
B: "is able to provide the present needs of members.",
C: "has a lot f money to lend to others out of the family",
D: "has a lot of money to spend on its members",
answer: "A. is able to provide the present and future needs of members",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The process of helping individuals to become informed consumers is",
A: "consumerism",
B: "consumption",
C: "consumer education",
D: "information technology",
answer: "C. consumer education",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. A plan showing how to spend total money earned is referred to as",
A: "household",
B: "household expenditure",
C: "inventory",
D: "shopping list",
answer: "B. household expenditure",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. A practical that can lead to an intelligent consumption of goods and services is",
A: "comparing values and buying in bulk",
B: "endeavouring to make most purchases on credit",
C: "making decisions that are influenced by the sales person",
D: "making unplanned purchases when shopping",
answer: "A. comparing values and buying in bulk",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. To ensure a restful background in the bedroom, use",
A: "cool colours",
B: "diagonal lines",
C: "vertical lines",
D: "warm colours",
answer: "A. cool colours",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Element of design include",
A: "harmony, lines and texture",
B: "space, harmony and line",
C: "space, line and texture",
D: "texture, space and rhythm",
answer: "C. space, line and texture",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Why are goods and services provided by family members considered as income?",
A: "Family members would have to pay for them if they were not available",
B: "They are considered very important to family members",
C: "They are used by family members to supplement what they earn",
D: "Their value exceeds the cash incomes earned by the family members",
answer: "A. Family members would have to pay for them if they were not available",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. One notable characteristic of hard water is that it will",
A: "be easily soften by boiling",
B: "be soften by filtration",
C: "not form fur in storage containers",
D: "not form latter with soap",
answer: "A. be easily softened by boiling",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Furniture is arranged in a room to",
A: "allow privacy",
B: "give good appearance",
C: "please visitors",
D: "show a person’s status \n32. A very dirty and stained plastic bucket can be cleaned with",
answer: "A. allow privacy",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. *******************************",
A: "kerosene",
B: "lime juice",
C: "soap",
D: "water",
answer: "A. kerosene",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following choices would one make if one values good health?",
A: "A chocolate bar for snack",
B: "A cup of coffee before lunch",
C: "Chatting all night on phone",
D: "Thirty minutes· jogging in the morning",
answer: "D. Thirty minutes jogging in the morning",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. A non-grease solvent used for cleaning in the home is",
A: "carbon tetrachloride",
B: "kerosene",
C: "methylated spirit",
D: "water",
answer: "C. methylated spirit",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. What would one be doing after completing an activity when one sits to think whether the right choices have been made?",
A: "Comparing possible outcomes",
B: "Defining the problem",
C: "Evaluating results",
D: "Identifying alternatives",
answer: "C. Evaluating results",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The most important consideration in the choice of a house is",
A: "economic status",
B: "family size",
C: "location",
D: "neighbourhood",
answer: "C. location",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following people will serve as the strongest influence on adolescents behaviour?",
A: "Classmates",
B: "Family members",
C: "Parents",
D: "Peer group",
answer: "D. Peer group",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. When one buys a plot of land and pays fully for it, the ownership title to the property is known as",
A: "deed",
B: "freehold",
C: "indenture",
D: "leasehold",
answer: "B. freehold",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. For effective money management; one should",
A: "provide al wants",
B: "spend available income",
C: "spend within income",
D: "take bank loan",
answer: "C. spend within income",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Examples of barrier methods of birth control are",
A: "condom and diaphragm",
B: "diaphragm and sterilization",
C: "pill and condom",
D: "pill and sterilization",
answer: "A. condom and diaphragm",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. The family life cycle ends when",
A: "all the children start their own families",
B: "both parents are deed",
C: "parents stop having children",
D: "the last child starts working",
answer: "A. all the children start their own families",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. children’s right to security means they must be provided with",
A: "appropriate knowledge",
B: "basic needs",
C: "health care services",
D: "Love and affection",
answer: "B. basic needs",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Steps in planning are",
A: "identifying resources, setting goals, setting standards, organizing",
B: "organizing, setting standards, identifying resources, setting goals",
C: "setting goals, identifying resources, setting standards, organizing",
D: "setting goals, organizing, identifying resources, setting standards",
answer: "C. setting goals, identifying resources, setting standards, organizing",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Positive self-concept makes people",
A: "arrogant",
B: "confident",
C: "judgement",
D: "proud",
answer: "B. confident",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Walls, windows, floors and ceilings of a house are collectively called",
A: "accessories",
B: "arrangement",
C: "backgrounds",
D: "treatments",
answer: "C. backgrounds",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Some of the reasons why adolescents abuse drugs are  \nI. curiosity and adventure.  \nII. disorganized background.  \nIII. reading pornographic materials.  \nIV. to escape frustration.",
A: "I, III and IV only",
B: "I, II and IV only",
C: "II, III and IV only",
D: "I, II and III only",
answer: "B. I, II and IV only",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. A sexually abused child usually feels",
A: "deprived",
B: "guilty",
C: "loved",
D: "protected",
answer: "B. guilty",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. To simply work in the home",
A: "complete all the washing before hanging",
B: "grind vegetables separately for soup",
C: "make several trills to the refrigerator",
D: "use blunt knife to cut meat",
answer: "A. complete all the washing before hanging",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. It is important to manage time very well because it",
A: "can be saved",
B: "can be substituted",
C: "is always available",
D: "is limited",
answer: "D. is limited",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. One characteristic of a food consumer is his ability to",
A: "get information about goods and services",
B: "read magazines for advertisements",
C: "shop for goods at the open market",
D: "use locally produced goods and services",
answer: "A. get information about goods and services",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question51",
question:  "51. The family can derive service income from",
A: "backyard gardening",
B: "bulk purchasing",
C: "preparing family meals",
D: "using family’s own freezer",
answer: "A. backyard gardening",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question52",
question:  "52. Comparing costs of items with estimates in a budget is a way of",
A: "controlling spending",
B: "evaluating financial plan",
C: "identifying items",
D: "Organizing effort to implement plan",
answer: "A. controlling spending",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question53",
question:  "53. Work time refers to the time spent on",
A: "income earning activities",
B: "preparing family meals",
C: "shopping for household items",
D: "washing family clothes",
answer: "A. income earning activities",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question54",
question:  "54. A sexually transmitted infection (STI) that can cause blindness in babies of infected mothers is",
A: "candida",
B: "genital herpes",
C: "gonorrhoea",
D: "syphilis",
answer: "C. gonorrhoea",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question55",
question:  "55. One way of using service credit is",
A: "buying a dress",
B: "buying a refrigerator",
C: "using a mobile phone",
D: "using a landline phone",
answer: "C. using a mobile phone",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question56",
question:  "56. An example of a labour saving equipment used in the home is",
A: "cake mixer",
B: "grinding stone",
C: "mortar and pestle",
D: "spoon and mixing bowl",
answer: "A. cake mixer",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question57",
question:  "57. The importance of making a shopping list is to prevent",
A: "impulse buying",
B: "bulk buying",
C: "buying substandard goods",
D: "wasting of money",
answer: "A. impulse buying",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question58",
question:  "58. The most challenging stage in the development of an individual is the",
A: "adolescent stage",
B: "adult stage",
C: "infant stage",
D: "toddler stage",
answer: "A. adolescent stage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question59",
question:  "59. Children cease to look to their parents for all their needs when they",
A: "are gainfully employed and independent",
B: "are well educated",
C: "gain admission into the universities",
D: "start pursuing a career",
answer: "A. are gainfully employed and independent",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question60",
question:  "60. Good lighting in the homes should be provided for",
A: "accomplishing tasks",
B: "planning activities",
C: "saving energy",
D: "work efficiency",
answer: "A. accomplishing tasks",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]